Welcome to Dealmakers. I'm Sarah Sharp.
I'm a real deal attorney who helps
people buy and sell businesses every
day. And I'm going to tell you how to
stop getting your letters of intent
rejected so much. There are five things
you absolutely have to keep in mind when
you're deciding what you want to offer
on a business, specifically relating to
the purchase price that you're offering,
and I will line them all out for you.
The last one is really, really important
and is the number one reason that I see
people get their letters of intent
rejected. Before I go any further,
please like and subscribe. Um, it helps
a lot if you engage in this content. And
while you're at it, go check out
dealacademy.org for some classes and
courses so that you can become the
expert on letters of intent or any part
of buying a business. So, I created an
acronym for this. Let's say you found a
business, you want to buy it. This is
how you're going to remember how to
figure out and what to consider before
you settle on a purchase price. The
acronym is mafia because nobody knows
how to do business better than the
mafia. The original small business
folks. So number one market. What's the
demand? So is it a buyer market? Is it a
sellers market? Is it really hot right
now in whatever industry you're looking
at? It used to be really easy to pick up
like coin laundry and things like that.
Those are now inundated. The market is
it's a sellers game there now. So what
is the market? What are the pressures?
What negotiating capital do you have
relative to the other side right now?
Sometimes it changes seasonally as you
know I do a lot of accounting practices.
So what it's a real sellers market
usually in May and it's a total buyer
market by December. So you know what is
the market how strong is your offer
going to be relative to the other offers
that are going to be received? That's M.
The A in mafia is adjusted Ebella. So
you want to adjust your IBIDA or
consider it seller discretionary
earnings the profit of the business and
it's going to look a little bit
different based on whether you're going
to be owning and operating the business
or you're going to be hiring a
replacement owner operator. So if you
are going to be hiring a replacement
owner operator this giant profit that
you're seeing might need to be reduced
because you might want to take into
account that you're going to have to
hire somebody who can do as much as an
owner operator was doing and that will
compress your profit. So that compresses
your debt service coverage ratio and
also you know takes a little bit longer
to get to the profitable area that
you're looking to. So consider that
adjusted IBIDA. Then you get to F which
is relative. It's related to adjusted
IBIDA but quite separate financing
realities. So you do not oh my gosh
don't do this. Do not offer a purchase
price that you can't actually support.
And that's something I see every day
because people will look at the market
and say, "This is a phenomenal target. I
can't wait. So many other people are
going to be giving offers on this and
they'll look at the listing and see
what's requested and they'll offer that
without any consideration for whether
they can back it up. So unless you have
that cash that you also then want to
spend on this particular thing, you need
to before you make an offer, before you
put that letter of intent in, before you
settle on a purchase price, check with
your plan. How are you going to finance
it? A lot of folks are going to go
conventional loan. That's fine. But
check and make sure that you can do it.
Even if it's a heliloc, even if it's
part cash, do not think that you're
going to get 100% seller finance deal
unless that market demand is nil. Cuz
seller finance deals are a pipe dream
for the most part. So, unless you can
con somebody into a seller finance deal
because they've never seen the light of
day and don't know how the internet
works, you're going to be stuck with
having to pay cash, which nobody does.
Raise a round of investment from friends
and family, which is fine, but takes
additional time and is weird. Or just
other investor pools like a classic
search funder, that's okay, but same
thing. You've got to do all of these and
you're tripling your deals that you're
running simultaneously because you've
got deals going that way and deals going
this way and your deal with a bank. or,
you know, a lot of my businesses who are
buying are going to use a 7-day loan.
So, they're going to be dealing with a
SBA pro hopefully hopefully SBA
preferred lender because if you go with
like another bank that just really has a
great relationship with you and has one
guy who does SBA loans, then you're
going to find that they're going to have
to send it out to the government to get
underwritten. It's going to take a ton
of additional time. So, if you're going
with an SBA preferred lender, I have
lots of opinions about those, so please
reach out to me. If you're going with an
SBA preferred lender, you want to vet
your offer with them before you offer
it. It doesn't mean that it just like
that it's not a guarantee that they're
going to give you that, but at least
it's within the realm of reasonable. So,
financing realities are really
important. What I find in my area, since
I'm mostly working with folks who are
below the $5 million uh purchase price
range, is that a lot of the buyers are
looking at 7A loans. And so, one listing
will have lots of offers from people who
are subject to the same financing
considerations. And those banks, they
will finance something based on the
past, the history of cash flow, not
projected future. They are not
speculative at all. And that can be a
little bit, you know, mean to say maybe
about the banks that they only care
about the past and they're so
conservative. You also need to always
remember everything like put on your
hat. Always remember what the other
person's position is, right? And the
bank is not a startup financer. They
don't get invest in the next Facebook
and become a gajillionaire because they
made a great speculative investment.
Their best case scenario is getting
their money back with interest. So
they're not motivated to, you know,
invest in a bunch of things that are not
likely to pan out. They're going to be
conservative, of course. That's the
bank. that's a 7A loan. But if that's
the case, then you're not going to be
able to maybe compete with all cash or
with private equity or with crazy
multiples and lots of like conventional
loan seller finance investor money uh
rollover equity type of deals. So, just
pick a lane, figure out your purchase
price, figure out, you know, what the
financing limit is, what that ceiling
is, and you may find that there's a
target that receives a lot of offers
that are exactly the same because
they've all talked to the same bank and
they realize the same ceiling. On the
other side of that, I have had the same
target and I've had multiple buyers talk
to the same bank and even the same
banker about the same target based on
the same information result in
completely different offers because
people do different things with the
information the bank gives them. For
instance, a bank might say, "Oh, wow. I
mean, that's really high for that
multiple, but it's technically doable.
It's just at the top end." And when that
happens, several buyers might hear,
"Ooh, that's too high. I'm not going to
offer that." Whereas one buyer might
hear, "Cool. So you're saying there's a
chance and go for it. Even within those
same financing restrictions, your
ultimate purchase price offer might look
different person to person. So that's M
market demand, a adjusted IBIDA,
Financing realities, I industry
multiple. So you know, I hope this isn't
the first time you're hearing about the
term industry multiple. If you're on
this channel, pick up books, you know,
read a book or two and, you know, maybe
wait until you know a little bit more
before you make an offer because
industry multiples are real bread and
butter um in the buying a business game.
It is every one of them has them. Check
out the next code, the NICS code that
specifies which industry you're dealing
with and do some research on what
they're trading at. So you know you'll
see that okay in this industry people
are buying between 5 and 8x the adjusted
IBIDA or the SDE or they're trading
between.9 and 1.3x the gross revenue. I
don't care for purchase prices to be
based on a gross revenue model because
it doesn't leave any toe hold in the
deal for you to uh revise your purchase
price if it turns out something in
diligence is different than you
expected. So my preference is if you
have a letter of intent, you put your
purchase price in there, you show your
work, you explain what you based it on,
and you make that a multiple of adjusted
EBA or SDE or profit or any other
metric, then going to be able to vet
through the diligence process. So that
if then it's a lot less profitable
business than you initially thought, you
have an easy way to say, "Hey, I said
4.4x this multiple. I'm sticking with
4.4x, but this denominator changed." And
we all agree. And that's a really
comfortable way to, you know, provide a
level of dynamicness to your purchase
price. So figure out what your industry
multiple is and try to tie that to the
adjusted IBIDA in light of your
financing concerns. But have we spelled
mafia? No, we still have an A. And it's
the very most important thing that is
going to absolutely have people
rejecting your letters of intent right
and left and wasting a lot of time if
you forget it. Oh yeah, I should tell
you the most important thing. it is the
asking price. So, if you write your
letter of intent without considering
what the seller of this business
actually wants, it's going to get
rejected. And that's not just the
purchase price. I mean, don't waste your
time putting an offer in if the asking
price is completely astronomical and way
far and apart from what your offer is.
First of all, just don't waste your
time. If the asking price and what
you're offering are similar, you've done
all this diligence. You've checked out
the market demand. You've done your
adjusted IBIDA and your financing
considerations and your industry
multiple and you've done a bunch of
research and you've come to a conclusion
and you want to put together an offer,
you need to make sure that you are also
addressing what the seller cares about.
What their asking price is is partially
the number, but it's also other things.
Do they own the office that you're going
to be leasing from them? It might be
really important that you lease it from
them instead of another buyer who would
not be leasing the office and they'd be
left trying to find a tenant, right? Do
they have a lot of employees they really
want you to take care of? Well, specify
that you're going to be taking care of
those employees. Do they really care
about their clients and they want to
make sure there's a continuity of
wonderful services? Well, then like
specify that in your letter of intent.
Speak to what they care about the most
and explain how you're going to
accomplish it. So, if you have a
business and you have no experience
running a business like that, you know,
explain how you're going to get up to
speed and make sure that you address
what the seller's actual ask is in your
letter of intent. Use the language they
use in any correspondence you've had
with them and make sure you reference
back to it so they know that you're
listening. And with all of that mafia,
you will have a winning letter of intent
and your letter of intent won't get
rejected a million times. So, if you
found this valuable, you'll really
appreciate the next video. So stay
tuned.